Guide to the Green and Smith Company Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Green and Smith Company collection
1807-1847
MS 1407
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
4.5
(9 boxes)
The collection consists of blotters, daybooks, journals, and ledgers relating to the general store of Timothy Green and Richard Green in East Haddam, Connecticut. The firm was later known as Green and Smith, Green and Pratt, and F. W. Green and Co. Also included are materials concerning the sloop Amelia, the schooner Russell, and the ship Indiana.
Green and Smith Company
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the Account Books Collection, MS 29.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Green and Smith Company Collection consists of blotters, daybooks, journals, ledgers and other accounts which relate to a general store in East Haddam, Connecticut. The earlier records (1807-1820) are for a store run by Timothy and Richard Green, selling food, clothing, dry goods, and liquor. The volume "storage and ship book" indicates that the firm was also involved in shipping, storing goods until they could be sent on various ships. The volume records goods shipped on several trips of the sloop Amelia, schooner Russell, and ship Indian a.
Records for the period ca. 1822 to 1830 document the firm of Green and Smith (Timothy Green and Benjamin Fisk Smith), while the firm names of Green and Pratt and F.W. Green and Co. appear on records from 1831 to 1835 and 1836-1839 respectively. The records of Green and Smith are the most numerous and include daybooks, journals, or ledgers, which cover the entire period of the firm's existence. There is also an invoice book for the firm which includes accounts of payments for goods, as well as yearly (1823-1829) inventories of goods, and tallies of balances due on accounts, notes due, and capital stock. The 1823 account records the firm's worth at $15,100, with $12,900 in stock. The volume also includes several pages listing costs for the hull of the brig Venus. The daybook includes an accounts of "twine factory concern" with Timothy Green. The firm of Green and Platt is sparsely represented by two journals, while records of F.W. Green and Company include blotters, a daybook, and a ledger.
The collection was transferred from the Account Books Collection (MS 29) in 1985.
Business; General stores; Connecticut -- Commerce; East Haddam (Conn.); Account books; Blotters; Daybooks; Journals (bookkeeping); Ledgers; Businessmen; Green and Smith Company
- Inventory
  - Ledger, with indices, 1823-24 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Blotter, 1822 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Blotter, 1837 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Daybook 'F', 1818 September - 1820 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Daybook 'D', 1816-1817 June (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Daybook 15, 1825 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Daybook 16, 1825 December - 1826 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Daybook, 1827 August - 1829 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Daybook (with an account of "Twine factory concern to T. Green for stock," 1829-1847), 1827 March - September (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Daybook 'C', 1838 - 1839 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Blotter 'G', 1839 July - December (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Blotter 'E', 1838 October - 1839 March (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Index, undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Invoice book 'A', 1822 - 1829 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Journal 'C', 1824 June - 1825 February (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Journal 'D', 1825 March - 1827 February (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Journal, 1829 March - 1831 August (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Journal 'D', 1833 May - 1835 July (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Journal 'C', 1831 August - 1833 May (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Ledger 'B', 1825 March - [ca. 1823] (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Ledger, 1827 - 1833 (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Ledger, 1836 - [ca. 1843] (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Storage and ship book, 1807 - 1836 (Box 9, Folder 23)